The Power set is the set of all subsets. For example, if
we have the set  the power set is the following set.
So, it contains the individual elements,
the pairs of elements,
the whole set and the emptyset at the
bottom, which is a subset of every set.
We may notice that there are 2 to the power of 3 or
8 members in the power set of a set with three elements.
Since another way to look at the power set, is we
consider each possibility in the procedure of going by each element
in the set and either saying yes or no.
If we say yes to all elements, we get the whole set.
If we say no to each, we get the
emptyset, and then we get everything in between.
We will now use this to define the so-called Von Neuman Hierarchy of
sets V, which is often considered to be THE Universe of sets.
Again, we start with the empty set at the bottom, and
then successively take the power set of the previous level.
So we get the set with the emptyset at the first level, then
the emptyset plus the set with the emptyset at the second level,
And so on. This seems tame and boring, but this is
a hyper-exponential function, the size of each level is the size
of the previous level raised to the power of 2.
So, the third level has 16 elements, the fourth level
has 65 Thousand, and the fifth level has way more
sets than there are atoms in the Universe.
We can see that each level contains the next ordinal.
We can repeat this procedure indefinitely, resulting
in the structure which we call V_omega.
We can then add in the following
new axioms, to get the theory ZFC-INFINITY.
These two axioms only make sense if we have infinite
sets, so we don't need to worry about them.
The replacement axiom just states that our Set theoretic Universe is
closed under functions. Meaning that if we have a function defined
on a set, then the range is also a set.
And this is the axiom of separation, which given some pre-existing set
Y, allows us to separate out all of the sets in Y
which satisfy a certain property. Where to get a bit technical, by
property we mean a First order formula with one free variable.
For example, we can use the formula \exists x(x+x=y)
to separate the even numbers from the natural numbers.
This formula is only true if we instantiate y with an even number.
Note, that the restriction that we are separating the elements
from a pre-existing set is necessary to avoid paradoxes. Since,
without it, we could define the set X to be
the set of all sets which do not contain themselves.
This is defined by a simple formula with one free variable, yet we get
that X in X iff X not in X. Which is a contradiction.
But anyways, if we stop the construction of our Universe here, we
get a model of ZFC-Infinity, since we can show that each of
these axioms hold true in this structure, yet each set is finite.
However, this structure is logically equivalent to the
number line with addition and multiplication described earlier.
Meaning that both structures can be interpreted within the other.
So, this tells us that if we want to go beyond simple
elementary school math, we will need infinite sets. But infinite sets are
confusing and cause issues when trying to formalize all of math.